hi all welcome back to this Thursday
playlist and today we are going to
continue with our API testing Series
this is part two of this particular
series if you have not watched the part
one
um I would recommend you to watch that
in our channel uh which is uh basically
talking about how API scan works and how
you can send and receive API requests
and responses so in this particular part
we are going to talk about how you can
scan a particular API file or a URI and
a API scan will then build a project
with all the different messages
with requests and responses with all the
parameters everything filled in for you
everything ready uh to be executed okay
so as I said there are two options uh to
scan your API using Tosca one is the
file option and if you have got some
definition file for your API like a wsdl
a wadl a Swagger or open API you can
scan that particular file directly okay
and then there is a URI option again it
supports all the different versions or
like the wstl Swagger wadl and here also
you can provide a URI or a URL and then
you can scan that particular URL for
your API and Tosca will then build a
particular
folder and file structure with all the
different messages with all the requests
and responses okay so we are going to
look at both the options but let's first
start with the Ura okay
so for this example I am going to use
the pet store swagger.io
so it's an open API and I'm going to use
this for this particular demo okay
so uh let's go ahead and remove this
folder which we used earlier I don't
need this okay and I'm going to create
two folders here now one I'm going to uh
name it as file and the other I'm going
to name it as URI okay just to show you
uh the difference between the two okay
and now first we are going to start with
URI so I'm going to select this folder
and then I'm going to click on this URI
option so this particular window opens
and here I need to pass the basically uh
the end point for this API
and also in the advanced section if this
API has got some authentication which is
required you know before we scan this so
you can pass a username and password you
can also pass a proxy address username
and password if it is required okay
for this particular example it's not
required and so we are going to use this
URL which is uh swagger.json okay and we
are going to hit this here so
now click on OK
and you will see that inside this folder
now it is created in the folder called
Swagger pet store inside this we have
got different folders like pet store
user and this basically replicate uh
whatever you have in your Swagger
documentation you can see there are
three different resources one is for pet
inside pet I have got different get post
put requests right and similarly for
other resources like store or user I've
got again different requests okay
so these are the three different
resource locations and each has got
different request types so similarly
Tosca has scanned this page for you and
it has created three different folders
under three different folders then you
have got all the different request types
okay so we have got the post request uh
the port request and then the get
request
and and the get request right
so uh each one is embedded inside some
other file type but don't worry about
that uh we should be only looking at
these request types right so the post at
pet you can see the payload is already
there uh with some default values as
well right
similarly for put request for get
request we have already got a query
parameter and there is no payload
obviously uh the endpoint resource is
already filled in so everything is there
uh only thing which is missing here is
we need to provide a value for this
particular parameter so that um
Tosca has not filled in so whatever is
not filled in uh you can fill it in but
most of the structure uh like the
folders the all the requests all the
information for those requests are
already filled in okay and that is for
all the different requests in all these
different resource types within this API
okay
so that's how you can scan a particular
URI and the project structure with
everything will be created for you
similarly for the file we can do that
again I even need to click on the file
and I have already
created a Json file okay where it has
the same Source uh like what we saw on
the pet store Swagger documentation the
only difference is it is in the Json
format right so it is in a file
so I can select that file from my local
and then I can click on open and again
you will see the same kind of structure
is again created based on that
particular file okay so all the requests
and all the information all the folder
structure is already created based on
whatever information is stored inside
the Json file
okay and this is how the Json file looks
like so you can see uh it is in the Json
format with a different values and data
types right
so
Tosca can scan this file for you or it
can also scan this URI for you okay and
then it can find out all the different
information which is required to process
all these different request types and uh
only things may be missing would be
either the authentication or the
parameters which you need to fill in for
any post request or get request or any
type of request okay but this is a very
useful feature a very unique feature of
Tosca where it allows you to scan
different apis uh through different
files or Uris okay so apart from testing
or even checking your apis this is one
very good feature because it can really
cut down the time required to prepare
all these request types and all the
information inside this before you
actually verify anything on your apis
right
okay now we have seen how we can scan
different apis using both the options
file and URI and Tosca is also created a
nice folder structure with all the
requests and all the information filled
in but let's go ahead and see whether it
works right because that's the most
important part so let's pick up a one
particular API request and see if it is
still working uh with what Tosca has
scanned and prepared for us okay so I'm
going to go uh into the URI section and
I'm going to pick up this get find pets
by status I need to provide a value here
okay so if I look at the API information
so pet find by status get request this
is uh the request
and you can see here in the
documentation that status value needs to
be considered from one of these three
values right so I can copy one of these
values uh maybe available
I can put it here right so that's the
query parameter with the name and the
value
and now let's go ahead and send this and
let's see whether it is still getting us
the response okay
so as you can see the status code is 200
okay which means uh the request was sent
successfully and we have received a
response as well
so you can see here uh that it has
returned all the different pet names
which are available in the store okay
so this is how you verify after you scan
a particular API using the request
so that's all for this particular video
I hope you enjoyed it and it was useful
uh but this is how you can scan
different apis using a particular file
type or a URI and you can also basically
check all your API request types whether
they are working before you start
testing these apis which is the next
stage right where you create test cases
in Tosca commander and then you put some
verifications and you basically automate
the testing of this apis right
so that's what we are going to do in our
next video so do tune into our Channel
and do subscribe if you have not yet so
that you get notified when we post this
particular videos